+91-9962645223 Gurgaon, Haryana reachme.abhishek.kr@gmail.com

# **Abhishek Kumar**

# Senior Data Scientist

Portfolio: abhinine4.github.io github.com/abhinine4 linkedin.com/in/akumar58

Senior Data Scientist with 5+ years of experience in machine learning, computer vision, and NLP, with a Master's in Computer Science & Engineering (University at Buffalo). Proficient in Python, C++, and PyTorch. I'm currently building agentic systems to automate customer support and ticketing system. I'm seeking new opportunities to work as an Applied Scientist.

#### **SKILLS**

Language and Database Framework and Libraries Agents and Tools Python, C++, SQL, Java (familiar), MongoDB, Weaviate, MySql, Redis, ElasticSearch

PyTorch, Unsloth, Langchain, Django, FastAPI, Transformers, OpenCV, Sklearn, Kafka, SQS, vLLM Langraph, Google-ADK, Crew.ai, Git, Docker, Azure, AWS, Jenkins, New Relic, Grafana, Prometheus

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

### Senior Data Scientist Mobikiwk

FEB 2024 — Present

Gurgaon, Haryana

- User-Ticket-Service, Developed hierarchical AI Agents to automate user ticketing service using Google-ADK and LangGraph.
- Created MCP servers with **FastMCP** that provide context to the multi agent systems using our legacy APIs and interact with remote JIRA and Salesforce MCP tools to orchestrate ticket resolution.
- Architectured query gateway and history management services to accurately route and manage query state across sessions.
- **Vaarta-Vedh**, Developed a financial advisory chatbot using **NLP and Generative AI** that provides personalized tax and financial advice based on users earning and spending patterns and can handle multi-turn and multi-topic conversations.
- Developed text-to-NoSQL query generation module using LLMs, which processes 200+ unique categories/subcategories, payment methods, merchants and associated banks to create accurate NoSQL queries.
- Designed a **RAG** based **caching system** to store and query frequently asked user questions. Performed template matching with hybrid search for higher accuracy, and reduced latency by 70-80% and costs by 90%.
- Created a response generation module that uses a Llama3.2 3b model fine tuned on custom SOPs and guardrails to create structured responses. Trained with **PEFT(QLoRA)** and served using **vLLM**.
- Built an automated evaluation tool, lens-test-suite, to check for drifts and evaluate system responses.
- Bank-Statement-Parser, Developed a scalable credit card statement parsing service that uses OCR and large language models (Azure OpenAI) to extract and parse text data and send bill payment notifications to users.
- Created FastAPI service to consumes requests in batches from Kafka queues and processes them asynchronously using Asyncio.

## **Research Engineer**

SEP 2022 — FEB 2024

Artificial Intelligence Innovation Lab (A2IL)

Buffalo, New York

- Face-Morphing, Developed an image morphing system that uses latent diffusion models (Control-Net) to generate high quality face morphs of interpolated best pair images.
- Implemented latent interpolation and CLIP-based scoring to optimize image generation quality.
- Manipulation-Detection, Developed manipulation detection system to detect, localize, and label tampered news articles.
- Trained a CNN model using differential images with **ResNet-50** as backbone, to detect compression artifacts with 93% accuracy.
- Utilized NEDB-Net to extract noise and edge-based features to localize manipulations for the tampered regions.
- Fine-tuned a custom Yolo-v8 model to detect objects in the localized regions and label them into 18 categories.
- Engineered text-transformer tool for controlled entity and parts of speech replacements using **SpaCy** and **transformer (BERT)** models, enhancing data preprocessing for downstream AI tasks. Used **co-reference** resolution to maintain context in long texts.

### Systems Engineer Infosys

FEB 2018 — AUG 2020

Bhubaneswar, Odisha

- Trained a **Random Forest** model to classify independent and dependent system components with 97% accuracy.
- Built a part price prediction module using **linear regression** for refrigeration units, supporting faster data-driven quotations.
- Managed data workflows and CI/CD pipelines using **Jenkins**, **Git**, **Airflow**, **and PySpark**.

#### **EDUCATION**

Master of Science in Computer Science & Engineering, University at Buffalo, New York, GPA - 3.72/4, Masters Thesis Bachelor of Technology in Mechanical Engineering, SRM University, Chennai, CGPA - 8.8/10

AUG 2023 MAY 2017

## **PROJECTS**

#### Soccer Player Re-Identification

- Developed a deep learning model using Pytorch to re-identify soccer players in broadcast videos, achieving 63% mAP.
- Trained dual-branch network with ResNet and OpenPose subnetwork as backbones to learn appearance and body part features.
- Applied bilinear pooling to fuse appearance and body part features, enhancing robustness in dynamic scenes. Technical Report CNN-VAE Face Image Generation
- Built a CNN based Variational Autoencoder (CNN-VAE) in PyTorch to generate realistic face images, leveraging a custom dataset and latent space representations to learn meaningful facial features.